上次Gerry教授揭晓了秘密
PROFESSOR: Well, last time Gerry really let the cat out of the bag.
他介绍了赋值的概念
He introduced the idea of assignment.
赋值与状态
Assignment and state.
正如我们所见
And as we started to see, the implications
#TBD
of introducing assignment and state into the language are absolutely frightening.
首先 代换模型不再能够描述求值过程了
First of all, the substitution model of evaluation breaks down.
我们不得不使用更为复杂的环境模型
And we have to use this much more complicated environment model
这种带图示的机械式的东西#TBD
this very mechanistic thing with diagrams,
#TBD
even to say what statements in the programming language mean.
这不仅仅是技术上的一点 #TBD
And that's not a mere technical point.
代换模型在这里完全失效了
See, it's not that we had this particular substitution model and,
我们得想些其它办法
well, it doesn't quite work, so we have to do something else.
代换模型什么都做不了
It's that nothing like the substitution model can work.
因为突然地 一个变量不再是代表着一个值了
Because suddenly, a variable is not just something that stands for a value.
变量现在用来指定一个存放值的位置
A variable now has to somehow specify a place that holds a value.
并且在这个位置的值是可以变的
And the value that's in that place can change.
比如像(F X)这样的表达式
Or for instance, an expression like f of x
就可能含有副作用
might have a side effect in it.
如果我们执行(F X)得到某个值
So if we say f of x and it has some value,
之后我们再次执行(F X)
and then later we say f of x again,
可能因为求值的顺序而得到不同的值
we might get a different value depending on the order.
所以突然间 我们不能仅仅关注于值
So suddenly, we have to think not only about values
也要关注时间
but about time.
序对也不仅仅只是CAR和CDR了部分
And then things like pairs are no longer just their CARs and their CDRs.
#TBD
A pair now is not quite its CAR and its CDR.
It's rather its identity.
序对具有“身份”
So a pair has identity.
它是一个对象
It's an object.
两个具有相同CAR和CDR部分的序对
And two pairs that have the same CAR and CDR
可能相同也可能不同
well, might be the same or different,
因为这之中可能存在“共享”
because suddenly we have to worry about sharing.
一引入赋值 这些就变成要考虑的问题了
So all of these things enter as soon as we introduce assignment.
确实 这和我们说讲代换的时候差别悬殊
See, this is a really far cry from where we started with substitution.
技术上来看 我们思考起来更加困难了
It's a technically harder way of looking at things
因为我们必须相加机械地思考程序语言
because we have to think more mechanistically about our programming language.
而不能仅仅用数学的方式来思考
We can't just think about it as mathematics.
我们也会遇到哲学问题
It's philosophically harder,
我们会被这样的问题所困扰：
because suddenly there are all these funny issues
事物的“改变”指的是什么？
what does it mean that something changes
两个事物“同一”又如何判别？
or that two things are the same.
并且 这也会给我们编程带来困扰
And also, it's programming harder, because
正如Sussman教授上节课中讲的那样
as Gerry showed last time,
错误的序列和别名会产生BUG
there are all these bugs having to do with bad sequencing and aliasing
这些问题在不需要考虑“对象”的语言中 是不存在的
that just don't exist in a language where we don't worry about objects.
我们是怎样陷入这样的困境的呢？
Well, how'd we get into this mess?
我们这样做的原因在于
Remember what we did, the reason we got into this is
我们想要构造模块化的系统
because we were looking to build modular systems.
我们想把系统划分为数个自然组合的小块
We wanted to build systems that fall apart into chunks that seem natural.
举例来说 我们构造一个随机数发生器
So for instance, we want to take a random number generator
把该发生器的内部状态封装起来
and package up the state of that random number generator inside of it
这样我们就可以把选取随机数
so that we can separate the idea of picking random numbers
和用于估计的蒙特卡洛方法分离开来 #TBD
from the general Monte Carlo strategy of estimating something
#TBD
and separate that from the particular way that you
work with random numbers in that formula developed by Cesaro for pi.
相似地
And similarly,
当我们着手构建事物的模型时
when we go off and construct some models of things,
我们去构建现实世界中事物的模型
Ah, if we go off and model a system that we see in the real world,
我们想把程序组织成许多自然的部分#TBD
we'd like our program to break into natural pieces,
这些部分就是现实事物的镜像
pieces that mirror the parts of the system that we see in the real world.
举个例子 对于一个数字电路
So for example, if we look at a digital circuit,
我们会说
we say, gee,
这儿有一个电路
there's a circuit
它有一个这样的元件 有一个那样的元件
and it has a piece and it has another piece.
这些元件都有不同的“身份”
And these different pieces sort of have identity.
它们都有各自的状态
They have state.
状态附着在电路上
And the state sits on these wires.
我们认为这两个元件是不同的对象
And we think of this piece as an object that's different from that as an object.
当我们观察到系统发生了变化
And when we watch the system change,
信号从这里传递过来
we think about a signal coming in here
改变了可能存放在这里的状态 并向这里继续传播
changing a state that might be here and going here
和一个存储在这里的状态交互
and interacting with a state that might be stored there,
依次类推
and so on and so on.
我们想要在计算机中
So what we'd like is we'd like to build in the computer
构建模块化的系统
systems that fall into pieces
来反映我们对现实的看法
that fall into pieces that mirror our view of reality,
#TBD
of the way that the actual systems we're modeling seem to fall into pieces.
然而
Well,
构建像这样的系统
maybe the reason that building systems like this
看起来带来了不少技术上的麻烦
seems to introduce such technical complications
但这不是计算机造成的
has nothing to do with computers.
或许 我们花了那么大的功夫
See, maybe the real reason
才让程序反映现实世界的真正原因
that we pay such a price to write programs that mirror our view of reality
是因为我们对现实世界的认识出了错
is that we have the wrong view of reality.
或许时间只是幻觉
See, maybe time is just an illusion,
什么都没有改变
and nothing ever changes.
就拿这个粉笔来说
See, for example, if I take this chalk,
我们认为它是一个对象
and we say, gee, this is an object
它有自己的状态
and it has a state.
每时每刻 它都有一个位置与速度
At each moment it has a position and a velocity.
如果我们做点什么 就可以改变它的状态
And if we do something, that state can change.
但是你如果了解一点相对性的概念
But if you studied any relativity, for instance,
你可能不会认为粉笔的路径
you know that you don't think of the path of that chalk
是某种东西随着时间运动而形成的#TBD
as something that goes on instant by instant.
把整个粉笔的存在认为是时空中的路径，这是很有洞察力的 #TBD
It's more insightful to think of that whole chalk's existence as a path in space-time.
全部都展开了
that's all splayed out.
没有单独的位置与速度
There aren't individual positions and velocities.
只有在时空中不变的存在 #TBD
There's just its unchanging existence in space-time.
相似地 如果我们来考察这个电气系统
Similarly, if we look at this electrical system,
我们假设这个系统实现的是
if we imagine this electrical system is implementing
某种信号处理系统
sort of signal processing system,
#TBD
the signal processing engineer who put that thing together
doesn't think of it as, well, at each instance there's a voltage coming in.
转换成了某种东西
And that translates into something.
影响了这里的状态
And that affects the state over here,
还改变了那里的状态
which changes the state over here.
没有一个做信号处理的会这样想
Nobody putting together a signal processing system thinks about it like that.
相反 你会说
Instead, you say there's this signal
这里有一个在时间上伸展的信号
that's splayed out over time.
如果把这个看做一个滤波器
And if this is acting as a filter,
这个滤波器会把整个信号转化成
this whole thing transforms this whole thing
不同的输出信号
for some sort of other output.
你不必考虑在某个时间点上事物的状态#TBD
You don't think of it as what's happening instant by instant as the state of these things.
我们把这个盒子看做一个整体
And somehow you think of this box as a whole thing,
而不是在某些个特定时间的状态的集合 #TBD
not as little pieces sending messages of state to each other at particular instants.
今天我们将介绍另一种分解系统的方法
Well, today we're going to look at another way to decompose systems
站在信号工程师的角度去看待现实世界
that's more like the signal processing engineer's view of the world
而不再认为对象间通过消息传递来通信
than it is like thinking about objects that communicate sending messages.
它被称为“流处理”
That's called stream processing.
我们打算展示
And we're going to start by showing
如何让我们的程序变得更加统一
by showing how we can make our programs more uniform
从中看到更多的共性
and see a lot more commonality
如果我们跳出这些程序 #TBD
if we throw out of these programs
我们会发现
what you might say is a
#TBD
inordinate concern with worrying about time.
我们先来对比两个过程
Let me start by comparing two procedures.
第一个是这样
The first one does this.
想像这有一个树
We imagine that there's a tree.
一个由整数构成的树
Say there's a tree of integers.
一个二叉树
It's a binary tree.
看起来就像这样
So it looks like this.
在每个节点上都有一个整数
And there's integers in each of the nodes.
我们想计算
And what we would like to compute is
对这个树中所有的奇数
for each odd number sitting here,
计算它们的平方和
we'd like to find the square and then sum up all those squares.
我们对这类问题很熟悉
Well, that should be a familiar kind of thing.
有一种递归策略求解它
There's a recursive strategy for doing it.
观察每个叶子节点
We look at each leaf, and either
如果是奇数我们就求它的平方 并加和
it's going to contribute the square of the number if it's odd
如果是偶数 就是0
or 0 if it's even.
递归地看 对于每一颗树 我们可以说
And then recursively, we can say at each tree
它的平方和等于
the sum of all of them is
右子树的平方和 加上左子树的平方和
the sum coming from the right branch and the left branch,
就这样沿着节点递归下去
and recursively down through the nodes.
这种思考方式我们已经很熟悉了
And that's a familiar way of thinking about programming.
我们在幻灯片上看一下这个
Let's actually look at that on the slide.
为了计算一棵树中奇数的平方和
We say to sum the odd squares in a tree,
我们先要判断它是否是一个叶子节点
there's a test. Either it's a leaf node,
判断方法则是考察该节点是否为整数
and we're going to check to see if it's an integer,
继而判断其奇偶性 以及是否应该求取平方并加和
and then either it's odd, in which we take the square, or else it's 0.
然后 整个的解就是
And then the sum of the whole thing
左、右子树解的总和
is the sum coming from the left branch and the right branch.
好的 让我们再来和下面一个问题对比一下
OK, well, let me contrast that with a second problem.
假如给你一个整数N
Suppose I give you an integer n,
再给定一个函数 把它应用在
and then some function to compute of the first of each integer
1到N的每一个数上
1 through n.
我想把其中的一些值收集成一个表
And then I want to collect together in a list
那些满足某种属性的函数值
all those function values that satisfy some property.
这是种一般性的说法
That's a general kind of thing.
说得更具体一点
Let's say to be specific,
假设对于每个整数K
let's imagine that for each integer, k,
计算第K个斐波那契数
we're going to compute the k Fibonacci number.
然后挑出其中的奇数
And then we'll see which of those are odd
并把它们组成一个表
and assemble those into a list.
这个过程是这样的
So here's a procedure that does that.
寻找前N个斐波那契数中的奇数
Find the odd Fibonacci numbers among the first n.
这里是我们一直以来采用的循环方法
And here is a standard loop the way we've been writing it.
用到了递归
This is a recursion.
以K为循环变量
It's a loop on k,
如果K大于N 返回空表
and says if k is bigger than n, it's the empty list.
否则计算第K个斐波那契数
Otherwise we compute the k-th Fibonacci number,
将其与变量F绑定
call that f.
如果是奇数 我们把它与从K+1计算得到的表相连接
If it's odd, we CONS it on to the list starting with the next one.
否则 我们只取从K+1计算得到的结果
And otherwise, we just take the next one.
这是迭代式循环的标准写法
And this is the standard way we've been writing iterative loops.
我们以1为初值 启动这个循环
And we start off calling that loop with 1.
好的 就是这两个过程
OK, so there are two procedures.
它们看起来非常不同
Those procedures look very different.
完全不同的结构
They have very different structures.
然而 从一个特定的角度来看
Yet from a certain point of view,
两个过程做的事情是一样的
those procedures are really doing very much the same thing.
如果我是一个信号处理工程师
So if I was talking like a signal processing engineer,
我可能会说
what I might say
第一个过程枚举了树的叶节点
the first procedure enumerates the leaves of a tree.
可以认为是信号从一个全是叶节点的地方输出
And then we can think of a signal coming out of that, which is all the leaves.
我们想要过滤出其中的奇数
We'll filter them to see which ones are odd,
把它们放入某种滤波器中
put them through some kind of filter.
然后再把它们放入某种换能器
We'll then put them through a kind of transducer.
对每一个输出 我们对其取平方
And for each one of those things, we'll take the square.
最后把结果累积在一起
And then we'll accumulate all of those.
我们以0为初值
We'll accumulate them by sticking them together
通过加法把它们累积起来
with addition starting from 0.
这是第一个程序
That's the first program.
对于第二个程序
The second program,
我也可以用一种非常类似的方法来描述
I can describe in a very, very similar way.
我们枚举
I'll say, we'll enumerate
从1到N这个区间上的数
the numbers on this interval, for the interval 1 through n.
对于每个数
We'll, for each one,
计算对应的斐波那契数
compute the Fibonacci number,
再放入一个换能器
put them through a transducer.
对于输出的结果
We'll then take the result of that,
再通过奇偶性进行过滤
and we'll filter it for oddness.
最后 我们将这些放入累积器
And then we'll take those and put them into an accumulator.
这次我们要累积出一个表
This time we'll build up a list,
所以我们用CONS来做积累
so we'll accumulate with CONS
以空表为初始值
starting from the empty list.
从这个角度来看
So this way of looking at the program
这两个程序真的是太相似了
makes the two seem very, very similar.
问题在于
The problem is
两个程序的写法导致
that that commonality is completely obscured
我们看不出其中的共性
when we look at the procedures we wrote.
再回头来看奇数平方和的问题
Let's go back and look at some odd squares again,
问题来了 哪个是枚举器呢？
and say things like, where's the enumerator?
程序中哪一部分有枚举的作用？
Where's the enumerator in this program?
枚举不是仅仅在一个地方表现出来的
Well, it's not in one place.
在叶子节点的判断处存在一部分
It's a little bit in this leaf-node test,
#TBD
which is going to stop.
也下面的递归结构中也有体现
It's a little bit in the recursive structure of the thing itself.
累积器又在哪儿呢？
Where's the accumulator?
它也不只在一个地方
The accumulator isn't in one place either.
它在 0 和 + 这两个地方体现出来
It's partly in this 0 and partly in this plus.
累积器的完整过程并不体在唯一一个地方
Right? It's not there as a thing that we can look at.
相似地 我们来观察奇数斐波那契数的例子
Similarly, if we look at odd Fibs,
某种意义上 程序中也存在枚举器与累积器
that's also, in some sense, an enumerator and an accumulator,
但看起来非常不同
but it looks very different.
枚举部分地表现在(> k n)的判断中
Because partly, the enumerator is here in this greater than sign in the test.
部分地表现在下面的递归调用中
And partly it's in this whole recursive structure in the loop,
还有就是启动循环的地方
and the way that we call it.
同样地
And then similarly,
其中也混杂了累积器
that's also mixed up in there with the accumulator,
分别在这里
which is partly over there
和那里
and partly over there.
所以这些非常自然的部分
So these very, very natural pieces,
我们之前画的那些方框在程序中完全看不出来
these very natural boxes here don't appear in our programs.
因为它们混杂在一起了
Because they're kind of mixed up.
这些程序并没有很好地对问题进行切分
The programs don't chop things up in the right way.
回到计算机科学的基本原理上来
Going back to this fundamental principle of computer science
为了控制某种东西
that in order to control something,
你需要它的名字
you need the name of it,
#TBD
we don't really have control over thinking about things this way
because we don't have our hands in them explicitly.
我们没有一门好的语言来讨论它们
We don't have a good language for talking about them.
好吧 我们来创造一门合适的语言
Well, let's invent an appropriate language
用它来构建这些器件
in which we can build these pieces.
这种语言的关键在于
The key to the language is these guys,
这些叫作信号的东西到底是什么？
is what is these things I called signals?
这些沿着箭头传递的是什么？
What are these things that are flying on the arrows between the boxes?
这些东西
Well, those things
是一种称作“流”的数据结构
are going to be data structures called streams.
这也是发明这门语言的关键
That's going to be the key to inventing this language.
“流”是什么东西呢？
What's a stream?
和其它的东西一样 “流”是一种数据抽象
Well, a stream is, like anything else, a data abstraction.
所以 我先说明它的选择器与构造器分别是什么
So I should tell you what its selectors and constructors are.
对于流结构 我们有一个构造器
For a stream, we're going to have one constructor
我们称其为CONS-STREAM
that's called CONS-stream.
CONS-STREAM把两个事物放在一起
CONS-stream is going to put two things together
构造出一个流
to form a thing called a stream.
选择器叫作HEAD
And then to extract things from the stream,
用于从流中提取数据
we're going to have a selector called the head of the stream.
如果我有一个流
So if I have a stream,
我可以取它的头部
I can take its head
也可以取它的尾部
or I can take its tail.
我把我和George的约定告诉你
And remember, I have to tell you George's contract
让你们知道和这个相关的公理
to tell you what the axioms are that relate these.
对于任何的X与Y
And it's going to be for any x and y,
如果我把它们构造成一个流 并取其头部
if I form the CONS-stream and take the head,
(HEAD (CONS-STREAM X Y))
the head of CONS-stream of x and y
结果就是X
is going to be x
(TAIL (CONS-STREAM X Y)) = Y
and the tail of CONS-stream of x and y is going to be y.
一个构造函数 两个选择函数 一个公理 就是这些
So those are the constructor, two selectors for streams, and an axiom.
这里有点可疑
There's something fishy here.
你可能注意到了
So you might notice that these are exactly
这些就是CONS、CAR和CDR的公理
the axioms for CONS, CAR, and CDR.
把CONS-STREAM换成CONS
So if I said instead of writing CONS-stream I wrote CONS
HEAD换成CAR TAIL换成CDR
and I said head was the CAR and tail was the CDR,
这些就是序对的公理
those are exactly the axioms for pairs.
事实上 还有另一个东西
And in fact, there's another thing here.
我们有一个叫THE-EMPTY-STREAM（空流）的东西
We're going to have a thing called the-empty-stream
像空表一样
which is like the-empty-list.
为什么我要引入这个术语呢？
So why am I introducing this terminology?
为什么我不继续使用序对与表呢？
Why don't I just keep talking about pairs and lists?
后面我们就知道了
Well, we'll see.
暂时地 你们可以把
For now, if you like, why don't you just pretend
“流”当作“表”的另一种术语
that streams really are just a terminology for lists.
一会儿我们就会知道 为什么
And we'll see in a little while why
为什么我们需要这个额外的抽象层
why we want to keep this extra abstraction layer
而不是继续把它叫做表
and not just call them lists.
好的 有了流之后
OK, now that we have streams,
我们就开始构建语言了
we can start constructing the pieces of the language
用它来操作流
to operate on streams.
我们可以构建出太多有用的东西了
And there are a whole bunch of very useful things that we could start making.
举例来说
For instance,
我们构建MAP-STREAM 它的一个参数是流S
we'll make our map box to take a stream, s,
以及一个过程
and a procedure,
它会生成一个新的流
and to generate a new stream
#TBD
which has as its elements the procedure applied to all the successive elements of s.
我们以前见过类似的
In fact, we've seen this before.
就是以前在表上定义的MAP过程
This is the procedure map that we did with lists.
除了判断EMPTY-STREAM的部分
And you see it's exactly map,
完全就和MAP一样
except we're testing for empty-stream.
哦 我忘了说了
Oh, I forgot to mention that.
EMPTY-STREAM?就和NULL?差不多
Empty-stream is like the null test.
如果是空的 就返回一个空的流
So if it's empty, we generate the empty stream.
否则 就生成一个新的流
Otherwise, we form a new stream
其第一个元素是PROC应用在流头部的结果
whose first element is the procedure applied to the head of the stream,
剩下的是
and whose rest
是MAP-STREAM对流尾部应用的结果
is gotten by mapping along with the procedure down the tail of the stream.
太像我们之前讲的MAP了
So that looks exactly like the map procedure we looked at before.
还有一个有用的函数
Here's another useful thing.
过滤器 就是那个用来过滤的盒子
Filter, this is our filter box.
以一个谓词和一个流作为参数
We're going to have a predicate and a stream.
它将生成一个新的流
We're going to make a new stream
包含了在流S中所有
consists of all the elements of the original one that satisfy the predicate.
满足谓词PRED的元素
that satisfy the predicate.
这是一个“按条件分析语句”
That's case analysis.
如果流是空的 就返回一个空流
When there's nothing in the stream, we return the empty stream.
这里 用谓词来判断流的头元素
We test the predicate on the head of the stream.
如果为真
And if it's true,
就把这个元素
we add the head of the stream onto the result
和过滤流的尾元素得到的结果连接在一起
the result of filtering the tail of the stream.
否则 如果谓词判断为假
And otherwise, if that predicate was false,
就只返回过滤流的尾元素的结果
we just filter the tail of the stream.
这就是过滤器的原理
Right, so there's filter.
剩下的我快速过一遍
Let me run through a couple more rather quickly.
这些在书上都有 你们可以自己看
They're all in the book and you can look at them.
来马上过一遍
Let me just flash through.
过程ACCUMULATE
Here's accumulate.
ACCUMULATE的参数有：一个组合器
Accumulate takes a way of combining things
一个初始值和一个流
an initial value in a stream
将它们组合在一起
and sticks them all together.
如果流为空 返回初始值
If the stream's empty, it's just the initial value.
否则 我们就把流头部
Otherwise, we combine the head of the stream
和流尾部做ACCUMLATE的结果
with the result of accumulating
组合起来
the tail of the stream starting from the initial value.
这就是把流中元素累积在一起的方法
So that's what I'd use to add up everything in the stream.
我会用加法来累积
I'd accumulate with plus.
如何枚举树上的叶节点呢？
How would I enumerate the leaves of a tree?
如果这个树只是一个叶节点
Well, if the tree is just a leaf itself,
我就构造一个只含有一个叶子节点的流
I make something which only has that node in it.
否则的话 我就把
Otherwise, I append together the stuff of enumerating
左、右子树枚举的结果合并起来
the left branch and the right branch.
这里的APPEND-STREAM跟表上的APPEND类似
And then append here is like the ordinary append on lists.
再来看这个
You can look at that.
这跟和合并两个表的过程太相似了
That's analogous to the ordinary procedure for appending two lists.
如何枚举一个区间呢？
Ah... How would I enumerate an interval?
它有两个参数 LOW和HIGH
This will take two integers, low and high,
生成一个包含从LOW到HIGH的所有整数的流
and generate a stream of the integers going from low to high.
由此 我们就可以构造这一整串的元件
And we can make a whole bunch of pieces.
这就是一门用来讨论流的小型语言
So that's a little language of talking about streams.
当我们有了流
Once we have streams,
就可以构建由于操作它们的过程
we can build things for manipulating them.
请注意 我们正在构建一门语言
Again, we're making a language.
现在 我们可以用这门语言来表达我们的想法
And now we can start expressing things in this language.
这是累加树中奇数的平方的原始过程
Here's our original procedure for summing the odd squares in a tree.
现在你会发现 它和那些方块图如出一辙
And you'll notice it looks exactly now like the block diagram,
跟我们的信号处理方块图相吻合
like the signal processing block diagram.
要计算树上奇数平方和
So to sum the odd squares in a tree,
先枚举树上的叶子节点
we enumerate the leaves of the tree.
过滤出奇数
We filter that for oddness.
再用平方来做映射
We map that for squareness.
最后用加法来累积 初始值是0
And we accumulate the result of that using addition, starting from 0.
#TBD
So we can see the pieces that we wanted.
类似地 斐波那契数的那个问题
Similarly, the Fibonacci one,
我们如何获得奇斐波那契数呢？
how do we get the odd Fibs?
从1到N枚举整数
Well, we enumerate the interval from 1 to n,
再把FIB过程映射到上面
we map along that,
用来求取每项斐波那契数
computing the Fibonacci of each one.
过滤出奇数的部分
We filter the result of those for oddness.
最后 以空表为初始值
And we accumulate all of that stuff
用CONS将它们积累起来
using CONS starting from the empty-list.
那么 这么做有什么优势呢？
OK, what's the advantage of this?
首先一点
Well, for one thing,
我们现在有可以“混合与匹配”的元件了 #TBD
we now have pieces that we can start mixing and matching.
比如说
So for instance,
如果我想把这里改变一下
if I wanted to change this, if I wanted to ah...
想要计算整数的平方再进行过滤
compute the squares of the integers and then filter them,
我只需要
all I need to do
拿个像这里的MAP SQUARE这样的元件
is pick up a standard piece like this
放进去就行了
it's a map square and put it in.
又或者 如果我们想
Or if we wanted to do
寻找树的叶节点对应的斐波那契数
this whole Fibonacci computation on the leaves of a tree
而不是一个序列所对应的
rather than a sequence,
我只需要
all I need to do
用这个枚举器替换这个枚举器
is replace this enumerator with that one.
看到了吧 流处理的优势就是
See, the advantage of this stream processing
我们建立了 --
is that we're establishing--
这也是本课中的一个重要主题 --
this is one of the big themes of the course--
我们建立了一个通用的接口
we're establishing conventional interfaces
通用接口可以让我们把事物粘合起来
conventional interfaces that allow us to glue things together.
像MAP和FILTER这样的东西
Things like map and filter
可以作为一组标准的组件
are a standard set of components
我们可以拿过来随意组合去构造程序
that we can start using for pasting together programs in all sorts of ways.
它让我们看到了程序的共性
It allows us to see the commonality of programs.
虽然在这里
I just ought to mention,
我只是给你们演示了两个过程而已
I've only showed you two procedures.
但是我要告诉你
But let me emphasize
像这种用MAP、FILTER和ACCUMULATE
that this way of putting things together
组合起来构建程序的方式是非常非常通用的
with maps, filters, and accumulators is very, very general.
这是一种“生成-测试”的编程范式
It's the generate and test paradigm for programs.
举例来看
And as an example of that,
Richarc Waters -- MIT的一名硕士生
Richard Waters, who was at MIT when he was a graduate student,
他的学位论文的一部分调研了
as part of his thesis research went and analyzed
IBM的科学计算程序库
a large chunk of the IBM scientific subroutine library,
发现其中60%的程序
and discovered that about 60% of the programs in it
都可以用这样的范式来准确的表示出来
could be expressed exactly in terms using no more than what we've put here--
只用MAP、FILTER和ACCUMULATE
map, filter, and accumulate.
好 让我们休息一会
All right, let's take a break.
有问题吗？
Questions?
学生：整件事情的本质好像只是
AUDIENCE: It seems like the essence of this whole thing
因为你用了一个统一、简单的数据结构
is just that you have a very uniform, simple data structure
也就是流
to work with, the stream.
教授：对
PROFESSOR: Right.
本质应该是
The essence is that you, again,
#TBD
it's this sense of conventional interfaces.
因此你可以把许多东西组合起来
So you can start putting a lot of things together.
流只是 就像你说的
And the stream is as you say,
只是一种可以支持那样操作的统一的数据结构而已
the uniform data structure that supports that.
顺便说下 这非常像APL
This is very much like APL, by the way.
APL有着非常相似的思想
APL is very much the same idea,
只是在APL中使用的不是流
except in APL, instead of this stream,
而是使用数组和向量
you have arrays and vectors.
而且APL的威力就在于此
And a lot of the power of APL is exactly the same reason of the power of this.
好吧 谢谢
OK, thank you.
休息一下
Let's take a break.
好的
All right.
我们已经见识过了
We've been looking at
如何用流来组织计算过程
at ways of organizing computations using streams.
但是现在我想要给你们再演示两个
But what I want to do now is just show you two
更复杂的例子
somewhat more complicated examples of that.
我们先来考虑一下
Let's start by thinking about the following
这样一种有用的过程
kind of utility procedure that will come in useful.
假设我有一个流
Suppose I've got a stream.
流中的元素本身就是一个流
And the elements of this stream are themselves streams.
一开始是1、2、3
So the first thing might be 1, 2, 3.
就是这样的一个流
So I've got a stream.
流中的元素也是一个流
And each element of the stream is itself a stream.
而我想要构建出一个流
And what I'd like to do is build a stream
用来收集所有的元素
that sort of collects together all of the elements,
把所有元素从子流中提取出来
pulls all of the elements out of these sub-streams
最后把它们串接在一起
and strings them all together in one thing.
为了凸显使用这门语言多么简单
So just to show you the use of this language, how easy it is,
我们来定义这个FLATTEN过程
call that flatten.
FLATTEN过程的参数是由流构成的流
And I can define to flatten this stream of streams.
那么 具体定义是怎样的呢？
Well, what is that?
它只是一个累积
That's just an accumulation.
我想用APPEND来做累积
I want to accumulate using append,
也就是不断地做APPEND
by successively appending.
所以我用APPEND-STREAM做累积
So I accumulate using append streams,
以THE-EMPTY-STREAM为初始值 累积这个流
starting with the-empty-stream down that stream of streams.
这个例子告诉我们
OK, so there's an example of
你可以使用这些高阶过程
how you can start using these higher order things
来做一些有趣的运算
to do some interesting operations.
事实上 我还想定义另一个实用过程
In fact, there's another useful thing that I want to do.
定义一个过程FLAT-MAP
I want to define a procedure called flat-map,
它以一个过程和一个流为参数
flat map of some function and a stream.
#TBD
And what this is going to do is f will be a stream of elements.
F是一个过程
f is going to be a function
它作用于流中的每个元素 并产生一个新的流
for each element in the stream produces another stream.
#TBD
And what I want to do is take all of the elements and all of those streams
and combine them together.
所以对应的代码就是 (FLATTEN (MAP F S))
So that's just going to be the flatten of map f down s.
每当我将F应用在S的某个元素上
Each time I apply f to an element of s,
我得到了一个流
I get a stream.
执行完这条MAP语句后
If I map it all the way down,
我得到了一个由流构成的流
I get a stream of streams,
再把它进行FLATTEN
and I'll flatten that.
我想再使用这种方式
Well, I want to use that to show you a
来解决另一个大家很熟悉的问题
a new way to do a familiar kind of problem.
这个问题和我们以前遇到过的许多问题一样
The problem's going to be like a lot of problems you've seen,
#TBD
although maybe not this particular one.
给定整数N
I'm going to give you an integer, n.
我们的问题是
And the problem is going to be
找出所有的整数序对(I, J)
find all pairs and integers i and j,
其中 0 < J < I <= N
between 0 and i, with j less than i, up to n,
使得 I+J 是一个质数
such that i plus j is prime.
如果N=6
So for example, if n equals 6,
我在这儿画个小表格
let's make a little table here,
表头是I、J和I+J
i and j and i plus j.
比如说I=2 J=1 那么I+J就是3
So for, say, i equals 2 and j equals 1, I'd get 3.
然后I=3 J=2 那么I+J就是5
And for i equals 3, I could have j equals 2, and that would be 5.
I=4 J=1 I+J=5也是一样的 等等
And 4 and 1 would be 5 and so on,
直到I到了6就终止了
up until i goes to 6.
我想要这个过程产生并返回这样的一个流
And what I'd like to return is to produce a stream
就是像 (I,J,I+J) 这样的三元组组成的流
all the triples like this, let's say i, j, and i plus j.
对于每个整数N 我想得到一个这样流
So for each n, I want to generate this stream.
听起来很简单
OK, well, that's easy.
我们做做看
Let's build it up.
先这样开始
We start like this.
对于每一个整数 I
We're going to say for each i, for each i
生成一个流
we're going to generate a stream.
对于I从1取到N
For each i in the interval 1 through n,
每个I都生成一个流
we're going to generate a stream.
这个流将会是什么样子？
What's that stream going to be?
我们先生成所有的序对
We're going to start by generating all the pairs.
对于每个I 我们先生成
So for each i, we're going to generate,
对于每个从1取到I-1的J
for each j in the interval 1 to i minus 1,
我们先生成序对
we'll generate the pair,
也就是只含有I和J的表
or the list with two elements i and j.
因此我们对整个区间做映射
So we map along the interval,
生成序对
generating the pairs.
对于每个I 都生成一个序对流
And for each i, that generates a stream of pairs.
最后进行FLATMAP
And we flatmap it.
这样我们就生成了所有的(I, J)序对
Now we have all the pairs i and j,
其中I <= J
such that i is less than j.
就是这样
So that builds that.
紧接着就是过滤
Now we're got to test them.
我们对刚才FLATMAP得到的东西
Well, we take that thing we just built, the flatmap,
进行过滤 #TBD
and we filter it to see whether the i-- see, we had an i and a j.
I是表的第一个元素
i was the first thing in the list,
J是第二个
j was the second thing in the list.
我们用一个谓词来判断 表中的两个元素
So we have a predicate which says in that list of two elements
也就是表的CAR部分与CDR部分之和 是否为质数
is the sum of the CAR and the CDR prime.
用这个谓词对刚刚收集起来的表做过滤
And we filter that collection of pairs we just built.
就得到了我们想要的表
So those are the pairs we want.
然后我们继续
Now we go ahead
把过滤得到的结果 再次进行MAP操作
Now we go ahead and we take the result of that filter
用来生成 I、J 和 I+J 构成的表
we map along it, generating the list i and j and i plus j.
这就是过程 PRIME-SUM-PAIRS
And that's our procedure prime-sum-pairs.
最后只需要过一遍 这就是整个过程
Ok, and then just to flash it up, here's the whole procedure.
一个MAP、一个FILTER 以及一个FLATMAP
A map, a filter, a flatmap.
所有的东西都在这里了
There's the whole thing,
尽管可读性不是那么好
even though this isn't particularly readable.
我们只是把中间过程展开了
It's just expanding that flatmap.
这个例子
So there's an example
向我们展示了
which illustrates the general point
嵌套循环
that nested loops
在这个过程中 它看起来就像
in this procedure start looking like compositions of
各种嵌套的MAP和FLATMAP的组合
flatmaps of flatmaps of flatmaps of maps and things.
所以我们不仅仅可以枚举单个个体
So not only can we enumerate individual things,
通过使用FLATMAP
but by using flatmaps,
我们可以实现其它语言中的嵌套循环
we can do what would correspond to nested loops in most other languages.
当然
Of course,
重复写这些FLATMAP很烦人
it's pretty awful to keep writing these flatmaps of flatmaps of flatmaps.
尽管PRIME-SUM-PAIRS其中单独的部分很容易
Prime-sum-pairs you saw looked fairly complicated,
但整体看起来还是十分复杂
even though the individual pieces were easy.
如果你愿意的话 可以
So what you can do, if you like,
引进一个叫COLLECT的语法糖衣
is introduced some syntactic sugar that's called collect.
COLLECT只是一个缩写
And collect is just an abbreviation
用来代表特定顺序的FLATMAP和FILTER操作
for that nest of flatmaps and filters arranged in that particular way.
这里我们用COLLECT把PRIME-SUM-PAIRS写一遍
Here's prime-sum-pairs again, written using collect.
PRIME-SUM-PAIRS过程需要收集这样一个东西
It says to find all those pairs, I'm going to collect together a result,
它的元素是形如(I, J, I+J)这样的表
which is the list i, j, and i plus j,
而这将通过I从1取到N
that's going to be generated as i runs through the interval from 1 to n
同时J要从1取到I-1来产生
and as j runs through the interval from 1 to i minus 1
并且要满足I+J是质数
such that i plus j is prime.
课堂上我就不讲解如何定义COLLECT了
So I'm not going to say what collect does in general.
书上面有
You can look at that by looking at it in the book.
#TBD
But pretty much, you can see that the pieces of this
are the pieces of that original procedure I wrote.
COLLECT过程只是一个语法糖衣
And this collect is just some syntactic sugar
用来自动生成嵌套FLATMAP
for automatically generating that nest of flatmaps and flatmaps.
好的 我们再来看另一个例子
OK, well, let me do one more example
#TBD
that shows you the same kind of thing.
这是一个非常著名的问题
Here's a very famous problem
经常用来演示所谓的“回溯”算法
that's used to illustrate a lot of so-called backtracking computer algorithms
这就是“八皇后问题”
This is the eight queens problem.
这是一个棋盘
This is a chess board.
八皇后问题要求我们
And the eight queens problem says,
找到一种将八个皇后放到棋盘上的摆法
find a way to put down eight queens on a chess board
使得任意的两个皇后不会相互攻击
so that no two are attacking each other.
这里给出了一个解法
And here's a particular solution to the eight queens problem.
我需要保证摆放好后
So I have to make sure to put down queens
任意两个皇后不在同一行或同一列上
no two are in the same row or the same column
也不在同一对角线上
or sit along the same diagonal.
有一个解决这个问题的标准解法
Now, there's sort of a standard way of doing that.
首先我们要做是
Well, first we need to do is
站在George的层面 #TBD
below the surface, at George's level.
找到一种表示棋盘与位置的方式
We have to find some way to represent a board, and represent positions.
这个并不需要太担心 #TBD
And we'll not worry about that.
假设我们有一个谓词SAFE?
But let's assume that there's a predicate called safe.
SAFE?判断的是
And what safe is going to do
假如一些皇后已经放在棋盘上
is going to say given that I have a bunch of queens down on the chess board,
在这个点再放置一个皇后是否是安全？
is it OK to put a queen in this particular spot?
所以SAFE?的参数分别为ROW和COLUMN
So safe is going to take a row and a column.
我将尝试把下一个皇后放在那个地方
That's going to be a place where I'm going to try and put down the next queen,
另外一个参数是剩下的位置
and the rest of positions.
SAFE?要判断的是
And what safe will say
在这些位置已经放置了皇后的情况下
is given that I already have queens down in these positions,
在这行这列放置皇后
is it safe to put another queen down
是否安全
in that row and that column?
不用过分深究这个
And let's not worry about that.
那是George的问题 也不难写出来
That's George's problem. and it's not hard to write.
只需要检测该行、该列
You just have to check whether this thing contains any things
以及对角线上是否有东西即可
on that row or that column or in that diagonal.
那么 有了这个过程后 我们的程序该如何组织呢？
Now, how would you organize the program given that?
有一种传统的方式
And there's sort of a traditional way to organize it
我们称为“回溯”
called backtracking.
首先让我们来考虑
And it says, well, let's start of
把第一个皇后放在第一列的
let's think about all the ways of putting the first queen down
所有方式
in the first column.
有8种
There are eight ways.
先试下第一列
Well, let's say try the first column.
第一行第一列
Try column 1, row 1.
每个分支都代表了
These branches are going to represent
在每一个层次的可能解
the possibilities at each level.
我试着把皇后放在第一列
So I'll try and put a queen down in the first column.
现在 我在第一列放置好一个皇后以后
And now given that it's in the first column,
我又尝试在第一列放置下一个皇后
I'll try and put the next queen down in the first column.
并不成功 它们都……
That's no good, they're both...
我尝试把第一个皇后
I'll try and put the first queen,
把在第一列上的那个皇后 放在第一行
the one in the first column, down in the first row.
不好意思
I'm sorry.
放好后 我们再把下一个皇后放在第一行
And then given that, we'll put the next queen down in the first row.
这不行
And that's no good.
所以又回到这里
So I'll back up to here.
然后再考虑
And I'll say,
我们把这个皇后放在第二行吗？
oh, can I put the first queen down in the second row?
然而也不行
Well, that's no good.
那么放在第三行呢？
Oh, can I put it down in the third row?
这样可以
Well, that's good.
下一个皇后可以放在第一列吗？
Well, now can I put the next queen down in the first column?
我不能再画更多的棋盘了
Well, I can't visualize this chess board anymore,
但我先假设这个可行
but I think that's right.
我尝试下一个
And I try the next one.
在每一个地方 尽可能的沿着树往下
And at each place, I go as far down this tree as I can.
然后回退
And I back up.
如果我从这里往下走 发现下面不可能有解
If I get down to here and find no possibilities below there,
我就回溯到这里来
I back all the way up to here,
然后开始生成这个子树
and now start again generating this sub-tree.
我就像这样遍历
And I sort of walk around.
最后 一路求解下来
And finally, if I ever manage to get all the way down,
就会得到答案
I've found a solution.
这种典型的范式
So that's a typical sort of
之前被广泛地使用在人工智能编程中
paradigm that's used a lot in AI programming.
术语叫做 “回溯搜索”
It's called backtracking search.
这真的没有必要
And it's really unnecessary.
你们也发现了 我在可视化这个过程时也犯了迷糊
You saw me get confused when I was visualizing this thing.
你们也发现了 这很复杂
And you sort of see the complication.
而且这种复杂还很难描述
This is a complicated thing to say.
为什么会这样？
Why is it complicated?
这是因为
Its because somehow
这是因为这程序过分地关注于时间了
this program is too inordinately concerned with time.
这之中太多 -- 先试试这个 再试试这个
It's too much-- I try this one, and I try this one,
再回到上一个可行的地方 -- 这种操作太多了
and I go back to the last possibility.
这很复杂
And that's a complicated thing.
如果我们不再如此关注时间
If I stop worrying about time so much,
就有一个更简单的方式来描述
then there's a much simpler way to describe this.
让我们来想象一下
It says, let's imagine
现在我有
that I have in my hands
有一个高达K-1层的树
the tree down to k minus 1 levels.
假设我已经有了
See, suppose I had in my hands all possible ways
把皇后放在前K列的所有解法
to solve... to put down queens in the first k columns.
假设是这样
Suppose I just had that.
不要担心我是怎么得到的
Let's not worry about how we get it.
现在 如何扩充下去呢？
Well, then, how do I extend that?
怎样找到在下一列中放皇后的所有可行方法？
How do I find all possible ways to put down queens in the next column?
很简单
It's really easy.
对于已有的位置
For each of these positions I have,
我考虑把下一个皇后放在每一行上
I enjoin, I think about putting down a queen in each row
来构建出下一步的棋局
to make the next thing.
然后 把所有放置的位置
And then for each one I put down,
用SAFE?进行过滤
I filter those by the ones that are safe.
不像之前那样
So instead of thinking about
把这个树看做是逐步生成的
this tree as generated step by step,
我们假设所有的东西都生成好了
I say, suppose I had it all there.
为了从K-1层扩展到K层
And to extend it from level k minus 1 to level k,
我只需要扩展所有可能的放置方法
I just need to extend each thing in all possible ways
最后保留安全的排列
and only keep the ones that are safe.
就得到一个K层树的结果
And that will give me the tree to level k.
这是解决八皇后问题
And that's a recursive strategy
的一个递归策略
for solving the eight queens problem.
好的 我们来看看
All right, well, let's look at it.
我们编写子过程FILL-COLS
To solve the eight queens problem
来解决在一个特定大小棋盘上的
on a board of some specified size,
八皇后问题
we write a sub-procedure called fill-columns.
这个过程会把皇后放置到K个列中
Fill-columns is going to put down queens up through column k.
这是递归的模式
And here's the pattern of the recursion.
最后会以棋盘的大小为参数 调用FILL-COLS
I'm going to call fill-columns with the size eventually.
FILL-COLS是用来说明
So fill-columns says how to put down queens safely
如何安全地把皇后放置在
safely in the first k columns of this chess board
具有SIZE行的棋盘的前K列
with a size number of rows in it.
如果K是0
If k is equal to 0,
就不用做什么
well, then I don't have to put anything down.
结果是一个空棋盘
So my solution is just an empty chess board.
否则就做点别的
Otherwise, I'm going to do some stuff.
这里将要使用COLLECT
And I'm going to use collect.
完整的代码在这里
And here's the collect.
我找到了所有在前K-1列中放皇后的方法
I find all ways to put down queens in the first k minus 1 columns.
这是我所假设的 #TBD
And this was just what I set for.
想像这棵树下降到K-1层
Imagine I have this tree down to k minus 1 levels.
然后我尝试每一行
And then I find all ways of trying a row,
#TBD
that's just each of the possible rows.
总共SIZE行
They're size rows,
这里枚举了所有行数
so that's enumerate interval.
现在要做的是
And now what I do is I collect together
把我将要尝试的新行和第K列
the new row I'm going to try and column k
收集起来
with the rest of the queens.
我邻接一个位置
I adjoin a position.
这是George的问题了
This is George's problem.
实现ADJOIN-POSITION和SAFE?都是George的工作
An adjoined position is like safe.
这个过程需要的参数有
It's a thing that takes a row
ROW、COL以及REST-OF-POS
and a column and the rest of the positions
然后返回位置的集合
and makes a new position collection.
我把新的行和列
So I adjoin a position of a new row and a new column
和剩下的皇后邻接起来
to the rest of the queens,
那些剩下的皇后
where the rest of the queens
会尝试所有的
runs through all possible ways
放置在K-1列中的可行解
of solving the problem in k minus 1 columns.
新的行遍历了所有的可能性
And the new row runs through all possible rows
过滤出安全的位置
such that it was safe to put one there.
这就是整个程序了
And that's the whole program.
整个过程
There's the whole procedure.
它不仅找到了八皇后的问题的解
Not only that, that doesn't just solve the eight queens problem,
它还给出了所有的解
Right? It gives you all solutions to the eight queens problem.
运行结束之后 就得到一个流
When you're done, you have a stream.
流中的元素是所有的解
And the elements of that stream are all possible ways of solving that problem.
为什么这个更简单一点呢？
Why is that simpler?
我们完全没有把这个当做
Well, we threw away the whole idea that
按时间发生的、具有状态的过程
is some process that happens in time with state.
我们只说 这是一些东西的集合
And we just said it's a whole collection of stuff.
这是它更加简单的原因
And that's why it's simpler.
我们已经转变了观念
Right? We've changed our view.
还记得吗？这节课开始我们就讲过
Remember, that's where we started today.
我们转变了建模的观念
We've changed our view of what it is we're trying to model.
我们不再把事物看做按时间演进
we stop modeling things that evolve in time
也不再具有不同的阶段与状态
have steps and have state.
取而代之的是 我们对全局进行建模
And instead, we're trying to model this global thing
我们关注粉笔的整个飞行过程
like the whole flight of the chalk,
而不是专注于每个瞬时状态
rather than its state at each instant.
有什么问题吗？
Any questions?
学生：在我看来回溯会
AUDIENCE: It looks to me like backtracking would be
搜索到它所能找到的第一个解
searching for the first solution it can find,
而这个递归搜索
whereas this recursive search
会去寻找所有的解
would be looking for all solutions.
教授：是这样的
PROFESSOR: Right.
学生：但问题是
AUDIENCE: And it seems that
如果需要搜索的空间足够的大
if you have a large enough area to search,
第二种搜索方式就会变得不现实
that the second is going to become impossible.
教授：呃 这个问题其实是
PROFESSOR: OK, the answer to that question
这一节课剩下的内容
is the whole rest of this lecture.
这个问题很好
It's exactly the right question.
先不要尝试去预知后面的课
And without trying to anticipate the lecture too much,
只是在现在 你们要保持谨慎
you should start being suspicious at this point,
这里确实有点奇怪 难道不是么？
and exactly those kinds of suspicions. Isn't it?
尽管这个看起来不错 但是难道它不低效吗？
It's wonderful, but isn't it so terribly inefficient?
这是我们待会儿要解决的问题
That's where we're going.
就让我们稍后来揭晓秘密吧
So I won't answer now, but I'll answer later.
好吧 休息一下
OK, let's take a break.
现在你应该也开始怀疑了
Well, by now you should be starting to get suspicious.
我已经展示了这种简单而优雅的
See, I've showed your this simple, elegant
组合程序的方法
of putting programs together,
这跟那些传统程序非常不同
very unlike these other traditional programs
那些求奇数的平方和
that sum the odd squares
或者求奇数项斐波那契数之类的程序
or compute the odd Fibonacci numbers.
也不想那些混合了
Very unlike these programs that mix up
枚举器、过滤器和累积器的程序
the enumerator and the filter and the accumulator.
#TBD
And by mixing it up,
we don't have all of these wonderful
#TBD
conceptual advantages of these streams pieces,
these wonderful mix and match components
#TBD
for putting together lots and lots of programs.
另一方面
On the other hand,
#TBD
most of the programs you've seen look like these ugly ones.
为什么会这样？
Why's that?
#TBD
Can it possibly be
that computer scientists are so obtuse
#TBD
that they don't notice
that if you'd merely did this thing,
#TBD
then you can get this great programming elegance?
肯定有什么窍门#TBD
There's got to be a catch.
事实上这一窍门也很容易发现
And it's actually pretty easy to see what the catch is.
我们来看看接下来的这个问题
Let's think about the following problem.
假设我让你去找
Suppose I tell you to find the second prime
1,000到1,000,000之间的第二个素数
between 10,000 and 1 million,
如果你的计算机性能更强劲的话
or if your computer's larger,
或者可以去找10,000到100,000,000之间的
say between 10,000 and 100 billion, or something.
你可能觉得这很容易
And you say, oh, that's easy.
我可以用流来解决
I can do that with a stream.
我需要做的就是
All I do is I enumerate
从10,000枚举到1,000,000
the interval from 10,000 to 1 million.
我就获得了从10,000到1,000,000的所有整数
So I get all those integers from 10,000 to 1 million.
我过滤出所有的质数
I filter them for prime-ness,
也就是对这些数做素性检测
so test all of them and see if they're prime.
然后从中取出第二个元素
And I take the second element.
也就是 TAIL的HEAD部分
Right? That's the head of the tail.
这显然是非常荒谬的
OK? Well, that's clearly pretty ridiculous.
我们的机器没有这么大的空间
We'd not even have room in the machine
来存放这些整数
Right? To store the integers in the first place,
更别说来测试它们了
much less to test them.
而且我也只是取第二个数而已
And then I only want the second one.
这种传统程序设计风格的威力
See, the power of this traditional programming style
也正是其弱点
is exactly its weakness,
这种程序设计风格
that we're mixing up
混合了枚举、测试以及累积
the enumerating and the testing and the accumulating.
所以关键在于 我们不需要做所有的事#TBD
Right? We sort of don't do it all.
所以说 实际上这是这种
So by the actual... so the very thing
概念上丑陋的风格
makes it conceptually ugly
正是让它运行起来高效
is the very thing that makes it efficient.
就是像这样来混合
Right? It's this mixing up.
我今天一早上所做的好像都是在
So it seems that all I've done this morning so far
把你们搞糊涂一样
is just confuse you.
#TBD
I showed you this wonderful way that programming might work,
except that it doesn't.
但是 接下来就是见证奇迹的时刻
Well, here's where the wonderful thing happens.
结果却是 这个游戏里
It turns out in this game
我们真的可以得到蛋糕并吃掉它
that we really can have our cake and eat it too.
我的意思是
And what I mean by that
我们完全可以用流来组织程序
is that we really can write stream programs
就像我之前编写的那样
exactly like the ones I wrote
以至于当机器真正运行的时候
and arrange things so that when the machine actually runs,
它可以和传统风格的程序一样高效
it's as efficient as running this traditional programming style
那些混合了生成与测试的程序
that mixes up the generation and the test.
听起来不可思议
Well, that sounds pretty magic.
关键在就于
The key to this
流不是表
is that streams are not lists.
一会儿我们就会看到 但是现在
We'll see this carefully in a second, but for now,
先让我们来看看幻灯片
let's take a look at that slide again.
你们对这个
The image you should have here
信号处理系统的印象是
of this signal processing system
你们认为要发生的是
is that what's going to happen
在这类盒子中
is there's sort of this box
事先产生好了整数
that has the integers sitting in it.
这里有个过滤器
And there's this filter
它和那个盒子相连 并从中拉取东西
that's connected to it and it's tugging on them.
这里还有人从这整个系统中
And then there's someone who's tugging on this stuff
拉取东西
saying what comes out of the filter.
你们应该这么来理解：
And the image you should have is that
有人想要得到第一个质数
someone says, well, what's the first prime,
他从这个过滤器这儿拉取
and tugs on this filter.
FILTER从枚举器中去拉取
And the filter tugs on the integers.
#TBD
And you look only at that much,
and then say, oh, I really wanted the second one.
第二个质数是多少？
What's the second prime?
没有额外的计算
And that no other computation
只要你不去拉取东西
no computation gets done
就不会产生进行额外计算
except when you tug on these things.
我来用实物演示一下
Let me try that again.
这个小设备
This is a little device.
这是个小型的流机器
This is a little stream machine
这是Eric Grimson发明的
invented by Eric Grimson
他也在MIT教这门课
who's been teaching this course at MIT.
实际的流程是 -- 这里有某种流
And the image is ... here's a stream of stuff,
就像一串整数一样
like a whole bunch of the integers.
这些是一些处理单元
And here's some processing elements.
就像是FILTER、MAP之类的东西
And if, say, it's filter of filter of map, or something.
如果我把流实现为表 来进行处理
And if I really tried to implement that with streams as lists,
我拥有的是一个表
what I'd say is, well, I've got this list of things,
现在 我先执行第一个过滤器
and now I do the first filter.
我像这样完全处理
So I sort of do all this processing.
针对这个流
And I take this
不断地处理、处理、处理、处理
and I process and I process and I process and I process.
然后得到一个新的流
And now I'm got this new stream.
现在 我把得到的结果拿在我手中
Right? Now I take that result in my hand someplace.
然后把它放进第二个
And I put that through the second one.
又处理了全部的流
And I process the whole thing.
得到一个新流
And there's this new stream.
然后我再把结果
And then I take the result
用相同的方式再次处理
and I put it all the way through this one the same way.
如果仅仅把流当做表的话
That's what would happen to these stream programs
计算的过程就是这样的
if streams were just lists.
但是事实上 流不是表 流就是流
But in fact, streams aren't lists, they're streams.
而你们应该这样来想像
And the image you should have is something a little bit more like this.
我把这些小玩意连接起来
I've got these gadgets connected up
数据在其中流动
by this data that's flowing out of them. #LAST
这里是流的来源，开始生成整数
And here's my original source of the streams. It might be starting to generate the integers.
如果我想要一个整数，会发生什么？
And now, what happens if I want a result?
我揪住最后的这里
I tug on the end here.
这个元素可能会说，哥们，我需要更多的数据
And this element says, gee, I need some more data.
所以，这个到这里，又开始揪住那个
So this one comes here and tugs on that one.
同样说，哥们，给我来点数据
And it says, gee, I need some more data.
然后这个又揪住了下一个东西，可能是一个fiiler，哥们，来点数据啊
And this one tugs on this thing, which might be a filter, and says, gee, I need some more data.
最后的这一点东西，只有在去揪它的时候才会生成
And only as much of this thing at the end here gets generated as I tugged.
只有我去揪住末尾这里的时候，才会有数据通过这些元件得到处理
And only as much of this stuff goes through the processing units as I'm pulling on the end I need.
把流当作流和把流当作列表，就是这样的区别
That's the image you should have of the difference between implementing what we're actually going to do and if streams were lists.
说了这么多，到底怎么来实现呢？
Well, how do we make this thing?
我希望你们这样来想
I hope you have the image.
窍门在于如何构造流
The trick is how to make it.
我们想要把流组织成一种有需要时才会逐渐计算得到自身元素的数据结构
We want to arrange for a stream to be a data structure that computes itself incrementally, an on-demand data structure.
基本思想在于，再次强调，这种思想贯穿整个课程
And the basic idea is, again, one of the very basic ideas that we're seeing throughout the whole course.
那就是，数据与过程之间并没有绝对的界限
And that is that there's not a firm distinction between programs and data.
流会是这样的一种结构，你可以想象树的叶子的流
So what a stream is going to be is simultaneously this data structure that you think of, like the stream of the leaves of this tree.
但是不得不说，其中包含着计算方法的过程着实很精妙
But at the same time, it's going to be a very clever procedure that has the method of computing in it.
好吧，实际来看一下
Well, let me try this.
事实上我们不需要其它高深的原理
It's going to turn out that we don't need any more mechanism.
这个事实已经有了我们所需要的一切东西，那就是了解如何把过程作为一级对象来处理
We already have everything we need simply from the fact that we know how to handle procedures as first-class objects.
来看看这个关键之处
Well, let's go back to the key.
关键是，记住，我们有实际的操作方法
The key is, remember, we had these operations.
CONS-STREAM HEAD TAIL
CONS-stream and head and tail.
一开始，你可以把这个想像成CONS，这个是CAR，这个是CDR，事实上没这么简单
When I started, I said you can think about this as CONS and think about this as CAR and think about that as CDR, but it's not.
现在我们来具体看看它们到底是什么
Now, let's look at what they really are.
(CONS-STREAM X Y) 是这个东西的缩写形式
Well, CONS-stream of x and y is going to be an abbreviation for the following thing.
(CONS X (DELAY Y))
CONS form a pair, ordinary CONS, of x to a thing called delay of y.
在我具体解释清楚之前，先把剩下的写完，(HEAD S) 就是 (CAR S)
And before I explain that, let me go and write the rest. The head of a stream is going to be just the CAR.
(TAIL S) 是 (FORCE (CDR S))
And the tail of a stream is going to be a thing called force the CDR of the stream.
我来具体解释一下
Now let me explain this.
DELAY看起来很神奇
Delay is going to be a special magic thing.
DELAY所做是取一个表达式，然后做了一个约定，有需要的时候再来计算我
What delay does is take an expression and produce a promise to compute that expression when you ask for it.
这里并没有做实际的计算
It doesn't do any computation here.
只是一个延期的约定
It just gives you a rain check.
承诺要做这样的事
It produces a promise.
CONS-STREAM所做的就是把X和一个计算Y的约定相组合
And CONS-stream says I'm going to put together in a pair x and a promise to compute y.
如果你想取头，就是序对的CAR
Now, if I want the head, that's just the CAR that I put in the pair.
关键在于尾操作，对承诺进行FORCE调用
And the key is that the tail is going to be-- force calls in that promise.
TAIL会说，好吧，遵守承诺进行计算
Tail says, well, take that promise and now call in that promise.
这才开始实际的计算
And then we compute that thing.
这就是它的实际工作方式
That's how this is going to work.
这就是CONS-STREAM，HEAD，TAIL的真实面目了
That's what CONS-stream, head, and tail really are.
具体演示一下
Now, let's see how this works.
我会非常小心的过一遍
And we'll go through this fairly carefully.
现在从计算10,000到1,000,1000中的第二个质数这个实例来看，那具体是怎么运行的
We're going to see how this works in this example of computing the second prime between 10,000 and a million.
好的，我们从这个表达式开始
OK, so we start off and we have this expression.
第二个质数 -- 就是(HEAD (TAIL (FILTER (PRIME? (E-I 10000 1000000)))))
The second prime-- the head of the tail of the result of filtering for primality the integers between 10,000 and 1 million.
这究竟是什么？
Now, what is that?
就是10,000至1,000,000之间到底是什么？好，如果你开始枚举之间的整数，就构造了一个流
What that is, that interval between 10,000 and 1 million, well, if you trace through enumerate interval, there builds a CONS-stream.
CONS-STREAM实际代换过来是(CONS 10000 (DELAY (E-I 10001 1000000)))
And the CONS-stream is the CONS of 10,000 to a promise to compute the integers between 10,001 and 1 million.
这也就是上面这个表达式
So that's what this expression is.
现在我使用代换模型
Here I'm using the substitution model.
我们可以用代换模型的原因是这里并没有涉及时间与状态的副作用
And we can use the substitution model because we don't have side effects and state.
这里还有一个计算10001至1000000的承诺
So I have CONS of 10,000 to a promise to compute the rest of the integers.
所以到现在为止，只有一个整数被枚举了出来
So only one integer, so far, got enumerated.
然后用filter去过滤
Well, I'm going to filter that thing for primality.
我们再来细看filter这个东西
Again, you go back and look at the filter code.
filter首先测试 (HEAD S)
What the filter will first do is test the head.
这里，测试到的是10,000，不是素数
So in this case, the filter will test 10,000 and say, oh, 10,000's not prime.
然后就开始递归的过滤TAIL的部分
Therefore, what I have to do recursively is filter the tail.
TAIL是什么呢？就是那个继续计算的承诺
And what's the tail of it, well, that's the tail of this pair with a promise in it.
开始计算尾了，尾说，好，我履行承诺继续计算
Tail now comes in and says, well, I'm going to force that.
履行承诺的意思是继续枚举10,001到1,000,000之间的整数
I'm going to force that promise, which means now I'm going to compute the integers between 10,001 and 1 million.
现在看起来像是这样
OK, so this filter now is looking at that.
现在，就又回到了最开始枚举的部分
That enumerate itself, well, now we're back in the original enumerate situation.
(CONS 10001 (DELAY (E-I 10002 1000000))))
The enumerate is the CONS of the first thing, 10,001, onto a promise to compute the rest.
现在filter又开始针对10,001进行过滤了
So now the primality filter is going to go look at 10,001.
又要开始判断是不是质数
It's going to decide if it likes that or not.
结果不是
It turns out 10,001 isn't prime.
然后再继续履行承诺计算下去
So it'll force it again and again and again.
然后，我觉得第一个质数可能是10,009
And finally, I think the first prime it hits is 10,009.
在这个点才停下来
And at that point, it'll stop.
这只是第一个质数，我们需要的是第二个
And that will be the first prime, and then eventually, it'll need the second prime.
所以，又开始了
So at that point, it will go again.
你会发现，你需要多少，它才生成多少，不多不少
So you see what happens is that no more gets generated than you actually need.
enumerator不会生成比filter的要求更多的数要它去过滤
That enumerator is not going to generate any more integers than the filter asks it for as it's pulling in things to check for primality.
filter也不会生成比你的要求更多的东西
And the filter is not going to generate any more stuff than you ask it for, which is the head of the tail.
看吧，这样的程序实际运行起来就像是传统的那种程序一样，尽管外表看起来不像
You see, what's happened is we've put that mixing of generation and test into what actually happens in the computer, even though that's not apparently what's happening from looking at our programs.
一切都很简单
OK, well, that seemed easy.
这种机制的所有神奇之处在于DELAY
All of this mechanism got put into this magic delay.
所以你会想，啊，这肯定是最难以理解的地方
So you're saying, gee, that must be where the magic is.
但是并不是
But see there's no magic there either.
其实你应该知道DELAY是什么
You know what delay is.
表达式的DELAY只是一个缩略词，那么，这个要履行计算的承诺到底是什么？
Delay on some expression is just an abbreviation for--  well, what's a promise to compute an expression?
(lambda () )，就这么简单
Lambda of nil, procedure of no arguments, which is that expression.
这就是整个过程
That's what a procedure is.
它的意思是，这个表达式将会被计算
It says I'm going to compute an expression.
FORCE又是什么？
What's force?
如何履行承诺？
How do I take up a promise?
FORCE一些过程，只是简单地运行它们
Well, force of some procedure, a promise, is just run it.
结束了，就是这样
Done.
并没有什么离奇
So there's no magic there at all.
总结一下，我们都做了点什么？
Well, what have we done?
我们说，传统的编程方式更有效
We said the old style, traditional style of programming is more efficient.
使用流来编程，程序更为明晰
And the stream thing is more perspicuous.
我们设法用DELAY，使流获得了和其它过程一样的运行效果
And we managed to make the stream procedures run like the other procedures by using delay.
DELAY所做的就是，把我们程序中的事件顺序与实际发生在机器中的事件顺序分离开来
And the thing that delay did for us was to de-couple the apparent order of events in our programs from the actual order of events that happened in the machine.
这就是DELAY的作用
That's really what delay is doing.
也是全部的重点
That's exactly the whole point.
我们放弃了这种想法，即过程结构与实际运行映射出清晰的时间性
We've given up the idea that our procedures, as they run, or as we look at them, mirror some clear notion of time.
放弃这种想法，我们给予DELAY以改变计算顺序的自由
And by giving that up, we give delay the freedom to arrange the order of events in the computation the way it likes.
整个思想就是这样
That's the whole idea.
我们分离了程序表面上的顺序与实际运行的顺序
We de-couple the apparent order of events in our programs from the actual order of events in the computer.
对了，还有一个细节
OK, well there's one more detail.
一个技术性的细节，但是也非常重要
It's just a technical detail, but it's actually an important one.
当你运行一些递归的过程时，就像(TAIL (TAIL (TAIL ... 这样
As you run through these recursive programs unwinding, you'll see a lot of things that look like tail of the tail of the tail.
它就会不断在流中通过CONS来计算构造新元素
That's the kind of thing that would happen as I go CONSing down a stream all the way.
每次我这样做，计算TAIL，都要执行过程计算出新元素，每次执行TAIL，都要再次计算，看起来这效率非常低，还不如列表，因为我进行了多余的重复
And if each time I'm doing that, each time to compute a tail, I evaluate a procedure which then has to go re-compute its tail, and re-compute its tail and recompute its tail each time, you can see that's very inefficient compared to just having a list where the elements are all there, and I don't have to re-compute each tail every time I get the next tail.
我们把DELAY稍微改写一下，就可以让整件事变得 -- 我先写一下
So there's one little hack to slightly change what delay is, and make it a thing which is-- I'll write it this way.
(DELAY )的具体内容是(MEMO-PROC (lambda () ))
The actual implementation, delay is an abbreviation for this thing, memo-proc of a procedure.
MEMO-PROC改变一个过程
Memo-proc is a special thing that transforms a procedure.
取一个没有参数的过程，转变其为只需要执行一次计算的过程
What it does is it takes a procedure of no arguments and it transforms it into a procedure that'll only have to do its computation once.
我们意思是，你给它一个过程
And what I mean by that is, you give it a procedure.
MEMO-PROC的结果是一个新的过程，第一次运行的时候，它计算，记下来它的结果，从那之后，每次你再运行这个过程，就不用再计算了
The result of memo-proc will be a new procedure, which the first time you call it, will run the original procedure, remember what result it got, and then from ever on after, when you call it, it just won't have to do the computation.
它会把结果存储在一个地方
It will have cached that result someplace.
可以这样来实现MEMO-PROC
And here's an implementation of memo-proc.
一旦你了解怎么做，实现就很容易了
Once you have the idea, it's easy to implement.
MEMO-PROC中，有两个标记变量
Memo-proc is this little thing that has two little flags in there.
一个是，记录是否运行过
It says, have I already been run?
初始值是NO，还没运行过
And initially it says, no, I haven't already been run.
上一次运行后，它的结果是什么？
And what was the result I got the last time I was run?
MEMO-PROC取一个参数为PROC，返回一个没有参数的过程
So memo-proc takes a procedure called proc, and it returns a new procedure of no arguments.
PROC也是一个没有参数的过程
Proc is supposed to be a procedure of no arguments.
如果没有运行过，就做下面的事情
And it says, oh, if I'm not already run, then I'm going to do a sequence of things.
计算PROC，存储它的值
I'm going to compute proc, I'm going to save that.
存储在变量RESULT中
I'm going to stash that in the variable result.
然后对already-run?赋值，提醒自己已经运行过了，最后返回result
I'm going to make a note to myself that I've already been run, and then I'll return the result.
所以整件事即如果你没有运行过，就计算一次
So that's if you compute it if it's not already run.
如果已经运行过，直接返回结果就好了
If you call it and it's already been run, it just returns the result.
这是一种叫“记忆化”的小技巧
So that's a little clever hack called memorization.
这样的话，这一串东西就不会来反复的计算TAIL了
And in this case, it short circuits having to re-compute the tail of the tail of the tail of the tail of the tail.
不再那样的没效率了
So there isn't even that kind of inefficiency.
事实上，这样做甚至和传统的那种程序效率是一样的
And in fact, the streams will run with pretty much the same efficiency as the other programs precisely.
记住，再次提醒，整个的思想在于，过程与数据之间没有一个明确的分界线
And remember, again, the whole idea of this is that we've used the fact that there's no really good dividing line between procedures and data.
这个数据结构看起来，有点像一个过程
We've written data structures that, in fact, are sort of like procedures.
它使我们可以在这里放置一个结构，不断的迭代计算自身
And what that's allowed us to do is take an example of a common control structure, in this place iteration.
我们构造的这个数据结构，其中有一个过程，这个过程可以通过迭代，产生新的结构
And we've built a data structure which, since itself is a procedure, kind of has this iteration control structure in it.
这就是流的实质
And that's really what streams are.
好的，大家有什么问题吗？
OK, questions?
我是这样理解的，你刚才说(TAIL (TAIL (TAIL ...，没有没有MEMO-PROC的话，FORCE仅仅只是执行了一次过程而已
AUDIENCE: Your description of tail-tail-tail, if I understand it correctly, force is actually execution of a procedure, if it's done without this memo-proc thing.
你说使用那个MEMO-PROC就不会有那样的问题
And you implied that memo-proc gets around that problem.
难道(TAIL (TAIL (TAIL ... 不是每次都在进行计算吗？ -- [教授]哦，对的
Doesn't it only get around it if tail-tail-tail is always executing exactly the same-- PROFESSOR: Oh, that's-- sure.
我忘记说了
PROFESSOR: I guess I missed that point.
你是对的
PROFESSOR: Oh, sure.
不小心漏掉了这点
I mean the point is--  yeah.
我的意思是，不用重复计算也可以得到结果
I mean I have to do a computation to get the answer.
关键在于，一旦你计算过(TAIL STREAM)，当你计算(TAIL (TAIL STREAM))的时候，就不用再计算第一个TAIL了
But the point is, once I've found the tail of the stream, to get the tail of the tail, I shouldn't have had to re-compute the first tail.
明白了吧，如果我没有用MEMO-PROC，还要再计算一遍(TAIL STREAM)
See, and if I didn't use memo-proc, that re-computation would have been done.
明白了
AUDIENCE: I understand now.
之前的例子中你提到过，我们可以使用代换模型因为这里没有副作用
AUDIENCE: In one of your examples, you mentioned that we were able to use the substitution model because there are no side effects.
如果流通过的一个处理单元 -- 如果有副作用呢？如果有了状态？
What if we had a single processing unit-- if we had a side effect, if we had a state?
我们还可以用这种流的结构吗？
Could we still practically build the stream model?
可能吧
PROFESSOR: Maybe.
很难说
That's a hard question.
我可能会花很长时间来探讨代换模型和副作用无法共存
I'm going to talk a little bit later about the places where substitution and side effects don't really mix very well.
通常情况下，除非你非常小心，否则副作用会把一切弄的很糟糕
But in general, I think the answer is unless you're very careful, any amount of side effect is going to mess up everything.
我不是很理解MEMO-PROC这个过程
AUDIENCE: Sorry, I didn't quite understand the memo-proc operation.
当你执行lambda的时候
When do you execute the lambda?
换句话说，当MEMO-PROC执行的时候，只生成了lambda表达式
In other words, when memo-proc is executed, just this lambda expression is being generated.
但是我不太清楚是什么时候执行的
But it's not clear to me when it's executed.
好的
PROFESSOR: Right.
MEMO-PROC所做的 -- 作为MEMO-PROC参数是PROC，一个没有参数的过程
What memo-proc does-- remember, the thing that's going into memo-proc, the thing proc, is a procedure of no arguments.
某个时刻，你会调用到它
And someday, you're going to call it.
MEMO-PROC把一个过程转化为另一个过程，某个时刻你会调用到它
Memo-proc translates that procedure into another procedure of no arguments, which someday you're going to call.
就是这个lambda
That's that lambda.
这里，当这一部分构造成为流的TAIL的时候，这个没有参数的过程，会在之后的某个时刻被调用到
So here, where I initially built as my tail of the stream, say, this procedure of no arguments, which someday I'll call.
相对应的，我把这一部分理解为是MEMO-PROC，某个时刻会被调用到的
Instead, I'm going to have the tail of the stream be memo-proc of it, which someday I'll call.
所以这个lambda，会在你调用MEMO-PROC得到结果的时候被调用，正如你之前设置过的一样
So that lambda of nil, that gets called when you call the memo-proc, when you call the result of that memo-proc, which would be ordinarily when you would have called the original thing that you set it.
我的意思是，你调用MEMO-PROC的时候，你只是返回了一个lambda
AUDIENCE: OK, the reason I ask is I had a feeling that when you call memo-proc, you just return this lambda.
对啊
PROFESSOR: That's right.
你调用MEMO-PROC的时候，返回了一个lambda
When you call memo-proc, you return the lambda.
你也没有执行，直到你第一次需要执行它的时候
You never evaluate the expression at all, until the first time that you would have evaluated it.
我这样理解对吗？你构造了一个列表，其中的元素还没有被计算
AUDIENCE: Do I understand it right that you actually have to build the list up, but the elements of the list don't get evaluated?
表达式没有被计算？
The expressions don't get evaluated?
但在在每一个阶段，你还是构造了列表
But at each stage, you actually are building a list.
嗯，我应该这样说
PROFESSOR: That's-- I really should have said this.
这个问题不错
That's a really good point.
但是，也不全对
No, it's not quite right.
因为实际发生的事情是这样的
Because what happens is this.
我先把这个画成序对
Let me draw this as pairs.
假设我要构造一个特别大的流，比如枚举整数，从1到1,000,000,000
Suppose I'm going to make a big stream, like enumerate interval, 1 through 1 billion.
就是1，和一个计算的约定
What that is, is a pair with a 1 and a promise.
就是这样
That's exactly what it is.
什么都没有构造
Nothing got built up.
当我继续的时候，FORCE这一部分，会发生什么？
When I go and force this, and say, what happens?
这个东西递归的产生了CONS
Well, this thing is now also recursively a CONS.
这个约定生成了下一个东西，就是2和一个约定
So that this promise now is the next thing, which is a 2 and a promise to do more.
一直这样下去
And so on and so on and so on.
所以你沿着流这样下来，并没有构造什么
So nothing gets built up until you walk down the stream.
因为这个东西不是列表，只是一个生成列表的约定，技术上来说，是一个过程
Because what's sitting here is not the list, but a promise to generate the list. And by promise, technically I mean procedure.
因此并没有构造列表
So it doesn't get built up.
我应该早点说的
Yeah, I should have said that before this point.
好吧
OK.
就到这里
Thank you.
大家休息一下吧
Let's take a break.